A Guide to the School Annuals Collection, 1888-1925
Christiansburg Institute Museum and Archives
Christiansburg Institute Museum and Archives
School Annuals Collection, 1888-1925
Christiansburg Institute Museum and Archives, Christiansburg Institute, Inc.
MS2020-03
0.21 linear feet; 1 box
Christiansburg Industrial Institute; Friends' Freedmen's Association
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The...
Alternate Form Available
...
Existence and Location of Copies
Friends Freedmen's Association Records, RG 4/024, Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College.
Historical Note
In November 1863, a group of Philadelphia Orthodox Quaker men organized "the Friends Association of Philadelphia and its vicinity for the Relief of Colored Freedmen. The group's name later changed to "Friends Freedmen's Association of Philadelphia." From 1860-1880, the FFA established schools for the children of formerly enslaved people, creating 46 schools in North Carolina and Virginia. States assumed responsibility for education by the end of the 19th century, making much of the FFA's relief work unnecessary. The FFA shifted its attention and financial support to Christiansburg Industrial Institute.
Christiansburg Industrial Institute was founded as a Freedmen's Bureau school in 1866 by Captain Charles Schaeffer Montgomery County, VA. The FFA provided financial support and management shortly after the Bureau disbanded in 1871. Under the later leadership of African American faculty and staff, the institute grew into a working industrial school that taught academic subjects as well as agriculture, carpentry, blacksmithing, printing, sewing, cooking, and home economics. It also managed the Hill School, a primary and intermediate school.
In 1934, the FFA gave the title of the Hill School to the Montgomery County School Board. In 1947, the FFA sold Christiansburg Industrial Institute to MCPS for one dollar on the condition that the school remained dedicated to the education of African Americans.
Scope and Content
Christiansburg Industrial Institute was an industrial school for African Americans in Montgomery County, VA. It was financially supported by the Friends Freedmen's Association, an organization of Philadelphia Quakers, from the 1870s to 1940s. This collection contains records and correspondence from the institute's faculty to FFA members, and the school's annual reports and catalogues.
Arrangement
Arranged in 3 series: 1. Monthly Reports, 1888-1892. 2. Annual Reports, 1908-1916. 3. Miscellaneous, 1917-1925.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Friends Freedmen's Association Records, Accession SFHL-RG4-024, Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College, Swarthmore College Libraries, Swarthmore College, Swarthmore, PA.
Index Terms
Subjects:
African Americans -- Education -- Southern States; African Americans -- Education -- Virginia; African Americans -- Services for -- Southern States; African American youth -- Education -- Southern States; Charities -- Pennsylvania; Charities -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Education -- Southern States; Freedmen -- Education -- Southern States; Freedmen -- Services for -- Southern States; Freedmen -- Southern States; Friends' Association of Philadelphia and Its Vicinity, for the Relief of Colored Freedmen; Nonprofit organizations -- Southern States; Schools -- Southern States; Society of Friends -- Charities -- Records and correspondence; Trade schools -- Virginia; Society of Friends -- Education; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- African Americans; Women in charitable work -- Pennsylvania
Corporate Names:
Friends' Freedmen's Association; Quakers -- Pennsylvania Quakers -- Societies, etc.
Genre and Form Terms:
American periodicals
Contents List
- Series 1: Monthly Reports
  - William Polk, principal, Monthly Report, 1888-1889
  - William Polk, principal, Monthly Report, 1889-1890
  - William Polk, principal, Monthly Report, 1890-1891
  - William Polk, principal, Monthly Report, 1891-1892
  - William Polk, principal, Monthly Report, undated
- Series 2: Annual Reports
  - Annual Report of the Christiansburg Industrial Institute, 1908
  - Annual Report of the Christiansburg Industrial Institute, 1916
- Series 3: Miscellaneous
  - Rosa Tolliver, Hill School Intermediate Department Certificate, 1917
  - Christiansburg Industrial Institute 26th Annual Catalogue, 1924-1925